ILGWU. Research Department wages and hours files, 5780/148
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Research Department wages and hours files
1938-1975
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Research Dept.
5780/148
23 cubic feet
23 linear feet
Records
This collection contains extensive files of hearings before, proceedings of, and memoranda and briefs submitted to the Department of Labor's Wage and Hours Division between 1938 and 1942, and 1950 and 1975. Committees represented in these files include: Apparel Industry Committee, Button and Buckle Manufacturing Industry Committee, Embroideries Committee, Hosiery Industry Committee, Knitted and Men's Woven Underwear and Commercial Knitting Industry Committee, Knitted Outerwear Committee, Knitted Underwear and Commercial Knitting Industry Committee, Miscellaneous Apparel Industry Committee, Special Industry Committee for Puerto Rico, Textile Industry Committee, and the Women's Apparel Industry Committee. Also included in this collection are records of the Department of Labor's Public Contract Division and Research and Statistics Division.
5510715
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
August 2011
EAD encoding:
Cheryl Beredo, August 2011
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Biographical / Historical
The Research Department of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) supported the administrative operations of the Union. The Research Department was organized to coordinate the ILGWU's investigative operations. It provided Union leaders with information on wages, working conditions, economic conditions, and other matters in the women's garment industry. The Department also collected and housed documents from Union administrative staff that were deemed substantive and of lasting value to the Union, whether produced internally or externally. The information gathered by the Department was of particular value during labor disputes and contract negotiations.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains extensive files of hearings before, proceedings of, and memoranda and briefs submitted to the Department of Labor's Wage and Hours Division between 1938 and 1942, and 1950 and 1975. Committees represented in these files include: Apparel Industry Committee, Button and Buckle Manufacturing Industry Committee, Embroideries Committee, Hosiery Industry Committee, Knitted and Men's Woven Underwear and Commercial Knitting Industry Committee, Knitted Outerwear Committee, Knitted Underwear and Commercial Knitting Industry Committee, Miscellaneous Apparel Industry Committee, Special Industry Committee for Puerto Rico, Textile Industry Committee, and the Women's Apparel Industry Committee. Also included in this collection are records of the Department of Labor's Public Contract Division and Research and Statistics Division.
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
5780. ILGWU records
5780/045. ILGWU. Research Department records
5780/056. ILGWU. Research Department collected documents
5780/078. ILGWU. Research Department reports
5780/105. ILGWU. Research Department records
5780/114. Apparel, Job Training and Research Department records
5780/123. ILGWU. Research Department records
5780/163. ILGWU. Research Department. United States NIRA hearing records
5780/168. ILGWU. Research Department records
5780/175. ILGWU. Termination Analysis log books
5780/209. ILGWU. Research Department records
General
"Permanent deposit"
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Research Dept.
5510715
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Reports on the Apparel Industry Volume 12 June
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Volume 11 June 14-16
- U.S. Wages and Hours Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Volume 7, May 8
- U.S. Wages and Hours Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Volume 6, April
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Volume 10, May 8-9
- U.S. Wages and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Volume 9, May 8-9
- U.S. Wages and Hours Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Volume 4-5, March 15-17
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Volume 2, March 16
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Volume 3, March 17
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Volume 1, March 15
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Textile Industry Committee Number 1, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Administrator's Findings, Opinion, and Wage Order for the Textile Industry. Volume 2, September
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Embroideries Committee Number 45, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Hearings Before the Industry Committee and the Administrator. Volume 2
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Textile Industry Committee Number 1, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Report and Recommendations of Industry Committee Number 1 for the Textile Industry to the Administrator. Volume 1, May
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Reports on the Apparel Industry. Volume 13, June
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Volume 8
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Hearings to Consider Recommendations of Industry Committee Number 2 in Regards to Washable Service Apparel, Garters, Suspenders, Armbands, Men's Neckwear and Scarves, and Handkerchiefs. Volume 16
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Hearing to Consider Recommendations of Industry Committee Number 2 in Regards to Rainwear Industry. Volume 16
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Hearing to Consider Recommendations of Industry Committee Number 2 In Regards to Embroidery Industry. Volume 16
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Hearing to Consider Recommendations of Industry Committee Number 2 in Regards to Ladies' Handbags, Coats, Suits, Separate Skirts, and Belts. Volume 16
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Hearing to Consider Recommendations of Industry Committee Number 2 in Regards to Covered Buttons and Buckles, Artificial Flowers and Feathers. Volume 16
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Hearing to Consider Recommendations of Industry Committee Number 2 in Regards to Robes, Infant and Children's Wear. Volume 16
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Hearing to Consider Recommendations of Industry Committee Number 2 in Regards to Blouses, Shirtwaists, Neckwear and Scarves, Corsets and Allied Garments, Women's Underwear, Nightwear and Negligees. Puerto Rico. Volume 16
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Hearing to Consider Recommendations of Industry Committee Number 2 in Regards to Dress Industry and Washable Service Apparel. Volume 16
- U.S. Wage Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Hearing to Consider Recommendations of Industry Committee Number 2 in Regards to Dress Industry. Volume 16
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Report and Recommendation of Industry Committee Number 2 for the Establishment of Minimum Wage Rates in the Apparel Industry. With Appendix. September, Volume 15
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Summarizing Testimony and Briefs Presented to the Apparel Industry Committee. May 17, Volume 14
- San Antonio Garment Manufacturers Association Petition for a Review of the Findings and Opinion of the Administrator, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Volume 19
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Brief of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America in Support of the Recommendations of Industry Committee Number 2. Volume 17
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Hearing to Consider Recommendations of Industry Committee Number 2 in Regards to All Products Made in Puerto Rico. Volume 16
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Women's Apparel Industry Committee Number 27, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Hearing in the Matter of the Recommendation of Industry Committee Number 27 on the Homework Problem. Volume 5
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Women's Apparel Industry Committee Number 27, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Hearing in the Matter of the Recommendation of Industry Committee Number 27 on Exhibits. Volume 4
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Women's Apparel Industry Committee Number 27, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Hearing in the Matter of the Recommendation of Industry Committee Number 27. Volume 3
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Embroideries Industry Committee Number 15, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Proceedings of Industry Committee Number 15 for the Embroideries Industry. Washington, Volume 1
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Women's Apparel Industry Committee Number 27, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Proceedings of Industry Committee Number 27. Exhibits. Volume 2
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Women's Apparel Industry Committee Number 27, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Proceedings of Industry Committee Number 27 for the Women's Apparel Industry
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Embroideries Industry Committee Number 15, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Administrator's Findings, Opinion, and Wage Order for the Embroideries Industry. Washington, Volume 3
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Embroideries Industry Committee Number 15, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Report on the Embroideries Industry. Washington, Volume 2, August
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Knitted Underwear and Commercial Knitting Industry Committee Number 8, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Administrator's Findings, Opinion, and Wage Order for the Knitted Underwear and Commercial Knitting Industry. Volume 2
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Knitted Underwear and Commercial Knitting Industry Committee Number 8, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Proceedings, Volume 1
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Knitted Outerwear Industry Committee Number 7, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Administrator's Findings, Opinion, and Wage Order for the Knitted Outerwear Industry. June 12, Volume 2, Washington
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Knitted Outerwear Industry Committee Number 7, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Hosiery Industry Committee Number 3, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Administrator's Findings and Wage Order for the Hosiery Industry. August, Volume 2
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Apparel Industry Committee Number 2, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Administrator's Findings, Opinion, and Wage Orders for the Apparel Industry. Volume 18
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Hosiery Industry Committee Number 3, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Report and Recommendation of the Industry Committee Number 3 for the Establishment of Minimum Wage Rates in the Hosiery Industry. May 15, Volume 1
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Women's Apparel Industry Committee Number 27, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Hearing in the Matter of the Recommendation of Industry Committee Number 27. Administrator's Findings. Volume 6
- U.S. Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division Economics Branch, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Memorandum on Homework in the Adjustable Shoulder Strap Branch of the Women's Apparel Industry. Number 27 (A). C2
- U.S. Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division Economics Branch, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Memorandum on Homework in the Adjustable Shoulder Strap Branch of the Women's Apparel Industry. Number 27 (A)
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Research and Statistics Division, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Economic Studies Submitted to the Special Industry Committee for Puerto Rico. Tobacco Industry. Volume 4. Washington, April
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Research and Statistics Division Section, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Economic Studies Submitted to the Special Industry Committee for Puerto Rico. Miscellaneous Industries, Volume 3. Washington, February
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Research and Statistics Branch, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Economic Studies Submitted to the Special Industries Committee for Puerto Rico. Canning Industry, Volume 2. Washington, February
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Research and Statistics Section, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Economic Studies Submitted to the Special Industry Committee for Puerto Rico. The Needlework Industry, Volume 1. Washington, September
- U.S. Wage and Hour Industry Special Industry Committee for Puerto Rico, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Proceedings. Needlework-Briefs Volume 2. Puerto Rico
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Special Industry Committee for Puerto Rico, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Proceedings Volume 4
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Special Industry Committee for Puerto Rico, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Proceedings Volume 1
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Special Industry Committee for Puerto Rico, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Miscellaneous Industries-Briefs, Volume 2a. Washington
- U.S. Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Applicability of the Minimum Wage to the Operations of the Fibers International Corporation, Volume 2
- U.S. Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Applicability of the Minimum Wage to Operations of the Fibers International Corporation, Volume 1
- U.S. Wage and Hour Public Contracts Division, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Report, Findings of Fact, and Recommendations of Industry Committees in Puerto Rico
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Special Industry Committee for Puerto Rico, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  Proceedings, Volume 3
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Special Industry Committee on Puerto Rico Number 4, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  June
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  Administrator's Wage Orders and Regulations, Puerto Rico. Volume 11, Washington
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Embroideries Industry Committee Number 45, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Hearings on the Minimum Wage Recommendations of the Industry Committee and the Prohibition, Restriction, or Regulation of Homework in the Industry. Volume 2. Pages 1195-1337
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Embroideries Industry Committee, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Hearing on the Minimum Wage Recommendations of the Industry Committee and the Prohibition, Restriction, or Regulation of Homework in the Industry. Volume 2. Pages 1015-1194
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Embroideries Industry Committee Number 45, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Hearing on the Minimum Wage Recommendations of the Industry Committee and the Prohibition, Restriction, or Regulation of Homework in the Industry. Volume 2. Pages 926-1015
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Embroideries Industry Committee Number 45, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Hearing on the Minimum Wage Recommendations of the Industry Committee and the Prohibition, Restriction, or Regulation of Homework in the Industry. Volume 2. Pages 697-925
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Embroideries Industry Committee Number 45, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Hearing on the Minimum Wage Recommendations of the Industry Committee and the Prohibition, Restriction, or Regulation of Homework in the Industry. Volume 2. Pages 488-696
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Embroideries Industry Committee Number 45, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Hearing on the Minimum Wage Recommendations of the Industry Committee and the Prohibition, Restriction, or Regulation of Homework in the Industry. Volume 2. Pages 264-487
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Embroideries Industry Committee Number 45, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  Hearing on the Minimum Wage Recommendations of the Industry Committee and the Prohibition, Restriction, or Regulation of Homework in the Industry. Volume 2. Pages 147-263
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Embroideries Industry Committee Number 45, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  Hearing on the Minimum Wage Recommendations of the Industry Committee and the Prohibition, Restriction, and Regulation of Homework in the Industry. Volume 2, Pages 1-146. Testimony of Nathan Weinberg
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Embroideries Industry Committee Number 45, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  Proceedings of Industry Committee Number 45 for the Embroideries Industry. Exhibits. Volume 1
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Button and Buckle Manufacturing Industry Committee Number 43, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  Exhibits Submitted at the Hearing Before Industry Committee Number 43. Volume 2
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Knitted Outerwear Industry Committee Number 32, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  Proceedings of Industry Committee Number 32 for the Knitted Outerwear Industry. Volume 1
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Miscellaneous Apparel Industry Committee Number 31, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  Washington
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Knitted and Men's Woven Underwear and Commercial Knitting Industry Committee Number 28, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  Hearing in the Matter of the Recommendation of Industry Committee Number 28. Exhibits. Administrator's Findings. Volume 3
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Knitted and Men's Woven Underwear and Commercial Knitting Industry Committee Number 28, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  Proceedings of Industry Committee Number 28. Exhibits. Volume 2
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Knitted and Men's Woven Underwear and Commercial Knitting Industry Committee Number 28, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  Proceedings of Industry Committee Number 28. Volume 1
- U.S. Wage and Hour Division Embroideries Committee Number 45, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  Hearing on the Minimum Wage Recommendations of the Industry Committee and the Prohibition, Restriction, or Regulation of Homework in the Industry. Volume 2. Pages 1338-1550
- U.S. Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division Special Industry Committee Number 8, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Public Hearing for the Hooked Rug Industry in Puerto Rico. Volume 3
- U.S. Wage and Hours and Public Contracts Division Special Industry Committee Number 8, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  Public Hearings for the Needlework and Fabricated Textile Products Industry, Volume 6
- U.S. Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  Public Hearings for the Needlework and Fabricated Textile Products Industry, Volume 5
- U.S. Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division Special Industry Committee, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  Public Hearings for the Leather, Leathergoods, and Related Products Industry in Puerto Rico, Volume 8
- U.S. Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division Special Industry Committee Number 8, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  Public Hearings for the Needlework and Fabricated Textile Products Industry, Volume 3
- U.S. Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division Special industry Committee Number 8, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  Public Hearings for the Needlework and Fabricated Textile Products Industry, Volume 4
- U.S. Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division Special Industry Committee Number 8, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  Public Hearings for the Needlework and Fabricated Textile Products Industry, Volume 2
- U.S. Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division Special Industry Committee Number 8, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  Notice of Hearings and Recommendations of the Special Industry Committee to the Administrator, Volume 1
- U.S. Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  Hearing Before Special Industry Committee Number 7 Volume 3
- U.S. Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division, 1950` (Box 6, Folder 10)
  Hearings Before Special Industry Committee Number 7, Volume 2